<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A digest of government: together with certain additional proposals. Tendered to the consideration of all peaceable patriots. By William Ball, Esq</title>
            <author>Ball, William.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 10 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A77915</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B588A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R231631</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99897452</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99897452</idno>
            <idno type="VID">137107</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A77915)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 137107)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2487:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A digest of government: together with certain additional proposals. Tendered to the consideration of all peaceable patriots. By William Ball, Esq</title>
                  <author>Ball, William.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 7-11 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Thomas Johnson, at the signe of the Ke[y] in Paul's Church-Yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1659.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Page 7 has caption title: Additional proposals, &amp;c.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Political science --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Law --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:137107:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:137107:1"/>
            <p> DIGEST OF GOVERNMENT: TOGETHER WITH Certain Additional PROPOSALS TENDERED To the Conſideration of all Peace<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>able PATRIOTS.</p>
            <p>By <hi>William Ball,</hi> Eſq;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Thomas Johnſon,</hi> at the ſigne of the K<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                  <desc>…</desc>
               </gap> in <hi>Paul's</hi> Church-Yard, 1659.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:137107:2"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:137107:3"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="proposals">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:137107:3"/>
            <head>Additional Propoſals, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>FIrſt, That <hi>Explanation</hi> be made of all ambiguous Clau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and words, in any Law, Statute, or Act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which may admit of different, or indifferent con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions; that ſo the Letter of the Law may be direct, and plain (as in Reaſon it ought to be) and that ten Judges may not interpret the Law by way of <hi>Intendment,</hi> and ſeem therein rather <hi>dare ius,</hi> than <hi>dicere;</hi> by which means they have done, and may do, wrong.</p>
            <p n="2">2 That, (whereas, in regard of the multiplicity of Suits in Law, Hearings are delayed, and ſometimes put off from Term to Term, to the obſtruction or hinderance of Juſtice, and to the trouble, charge, and wrong of the Parties aggrieved), the Judges of the Courts at <hi>Westminster</hi> do ſit, and hear Cauſes (if they have any depending before them) on every <hi>Munday, Wedneſday,</hi> and <hi>Friday</hi> in the afternoon in the Term-time, and on the days commonly called <hi>All-Saints, All ſoules,</hi> the <hi>Purification,</hi> and St. <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> if it happen within the Term; (for certainly it is reaſonable to do juſtice on any day) and that the <hi>Lord Kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per,</hi> or <hi>Lords Commiſſioners</hi> of the Great Seal, and the <hi>Maſter of the Rolls</hi> ſit once every week (and oftner, if they ſee cauſe) in every Vacation: that Suits be not ſo long depending, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>layed in <hi>Chancery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3 That whereas <hi>Writs of Errour</hi> are ſomtimes neceſſary, and many times the cauſes of vexatious and chargeable delays, to the parties aggrieved; if erroneous Judgment ſhall therefore be found through Default of the Judges themſelves, ſuch Judges to be forthwith diſplaced, and utterly diſ-inabled to meddle in the Law, and ſuffer mulct according to their Demerits. And ſo touching the Barons of the Exchequer. And if ſuch erroneous Judgment ſhall be otherwiſe found, that the party or parties aggrieved be allowed quadruple Coſts and Damages; and ſo, if through the default of the Judges.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:137107:4"/> 4 That <hi>Demurrer</hi> be aboliſhed, and that if the caſe be mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Law, and not Fact, Judgment be forth-with given, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the merit of the cauſe; unleſs ſuch caſe be very diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult and then the Judges to meet within eight dayes in the <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chequer Chamber</hi> (as formerly) upon penalty of 100 <hi>l.</hi> for every Judges default who ought to meet; and then, and there to give a final Determination to the Cauſe.</p>
            <p n="5">5 That all Abators of Lands pay Quadruple Coſts and Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages, or ſuffer ſevere corporal puniſhment; and that all Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeizo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of Lands and Rents pay Quadruple coſts and damages.</p>
            <p n="6">6 That no relief be given in <hi>Chancery</hi> againſt the lawful En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try of Donors; F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>offors, and Leaſſors; that ſo their Acts and Deeds be not defalcated by way of Equity; and that all Bills of ſuch nature or pretext, be diſmiſſed of courſe, or not admitted into <hi>Chancery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7 That Deeds of Covenants to ſtand ſeized &amp;c. and Wills or Deviſes for Land invalid, or inſufficient, according to the <hi>Letter</hi> of the Law, be not made valid, or helped by way of Intendment, or Interpretation (which many times have been, and may be wreſted) of Law or Equity againſt Heirs at Common-Law: for it may ſeem to imply an act of GOD not to permit ſuch Deeds or Deviſes to be valid, that ſo Lands may deſcend according to His Law, <hi>Numb.</hi> 27. And therefore the defects of ſuch ought not to be ſupplyed by Man.</p>
            <p n="8">8 That un juſt Decrees in <hi>Chancery</hi> be reverſed by the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of State, or by ſome of them the eunto, appointed or nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minated; together with the aid or aſſiſtance of ſuch Judges or Serjeants at Law, as they ſhall think fit to call unto them; and that ſuch as made ſuch unjuſt Decrees be forthwith diſplaced, and ſuffer mulct according to their demerits: howbeit, ſuch as ſhall complain without juſt cauſe, to be ſeverely puniſhed.</p>
            <p n="8">8 That whereas there are divers covetous and greedy per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, who deſire and labour to incorporate as it were, and adde Lands to Lands, and will therefore venture to purchaſe any broken Titles, on purpoſe, by power of their purſes (being mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney'd men) to weary our ſuch as have better Right, thereby to obtain their Rights for little, or for ſome unvaluable conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on; and alſo to moleſt and contend with ſuch as have Rent-charges,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:137107:4"/> or other engagements in, or upon ſuch Lands, on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to make ſuch parties (eſpecially if mean and neceſſitous) to agree and compound with them to their loſſes; therefore all ſuch covetous and greedy Purchaſors, who ſhall be lawfully evicted touching Right, Rene, Charges, or other Engagements in, or upon ſuch Lands, ſhall pay quadruple coſts and damages.</p>
            <p n="10">10 That whereas divers covetous and greedy perſons do not onely themſelves, but alſo procure others (who may be termed <hi>Brokers)</hi> to inveagle young Heirs, and others, by flattery, feaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and merry-making, to ſell their Lands, Rights, or Intereſts, and at ſuch times, and in ſuch manner, obtain or get from them Agreements, or Contracts, for the ſale of their Lands, Rights, or Intereſts (many times upon unvaluable conſiderations, and ſometimes to their undoing) therefore all Agreements &amp; Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracts ſo obtained to be null. And alſo, that the perſons them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and their procurors (or <hi>Brokers)</hi> uſing ſuch practice, be ſeverely puniſhed.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="proposals">
            <head>Touching Commerce and Trade.</head>
            <p n="1">1 That a Council, or Committee of <hi>Audience,</hi> be inſtitu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed to ſit, hear, and receive ſuch Propoſals, as ſhall be exhibited unto them in writing touching the Commodities, diſcommodities, conveniences, inconveniences, advantages, diſadvantages, of Commerce, Trade, Manufactures; and of all Improvements, and Aggrievances, touching the Publique; and that the ſaid Council, or Committes do conſider, and propound to the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, ſuch advancements and furtherances, remedies and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſes, as the merits of cauſes ſhall require.</p>
            <p n="2">2 That, if our Neighbour-Nations, or other<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> more remore, ſhall raiſe the prices, or impoſe extraordinary Impoſt, or Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cize, &amp;c. upon their Commodities importable, into the Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions of this Commonwealth; we do the like for our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities tranſportable un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o them: Ours, of Tinne, Lead, Cloth, &amp;c. being as neceſſary and vendible unto them, as theirs to us.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:137107:5"/> 3 That no Fullers-Earth be tranſported out of this Land with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſpecial Licence from the Council of State, upon great penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; and, for that, ſufficient Excize to be impoſed: foraſmuch as not onely the Low-Countries, but other our Neighbouring Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, do thereby improve their Manufactures of Cloathing. &amp;c. and diſ-improve ours.</p>
            <p n="4">4 That Refiners of Sugar be not permitted to refine with Lime, as they uſually do; which is not onely a cheat, but un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wholeſome for bodily health; and that if there be no other Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy, ſuch manner of Refining be wholly prohibited.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="proposals">
            <head>Touching Elections of Members for Parliament.</head>
            <p>THat the Members for Parliament (for the future) do neither directly or indirectly, by themſelves or others, procure themſelves to be elected, upon penalty of being diſ-inabled to ſit in the Houſe, and to pay the Fine of 500 <hi>l.</hi> to the uſe of the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth:</hi> and that all Feaſtings, and Entertainments for Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions be aboliſhed upon like penalty: and that the Freehol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and ſuch as ſhould elect Members for Parliament, do aſſemble, and meet <note place="margin">
                  <hi>No Free holder under</hi> 10 <hi>l.</hi> per annum, <hi>to be admitted to elect Knights &amp;c. upon penalty,</hi> &amp;c.</note> for Elections at their own charges, upon ſome penalty, &amp;c. to the uſe of the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth</hi> (unleſs ſome lawful excuſe of ſickneſs, &amp;c.) And that if they happen to chuſe Knights for the ſhire, under the value of 500 <hi>l. per annum,</hi> and Burgeſſes for Boroughs under the value of 100 <hi>l. per annum,</hi> or ſome way equivalent; that they al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low them their <hi>Salaries</hi> towards their charges (if they ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, or deſire it) and not otherwiſe: and that ſuch members for Parliament as ſhall be <hi>legally</hi> ſo Elected (being perſons ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable to ſit in Parliament) ſhall undergo the ſame, upon penalty
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:137107:5"/> of 500 <hi>l.</hi> to the uſe of the <hi>Commonwealth</hi> (unleſs ſome lawfull excuſe of ſickneſs, &amp;c.) and that ſuch Elected Members ſwear before the Sheriff, and two, or one Juſtice of the Peace; or, in <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porations,</hi> before the Mayor, &amp;c. <hi>to perform their beſt endeavours for the places, for which they are elected; and for the Commonwealth in general.</hi> By this means, ſelf-ſeeking and ſelf-ended Members may be expunged; and yet ſufficient, able, and knowing men elected.</p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
